The brutal Burmese military operation
against Rohingya Muslims
is at risk of spiralling into
an ethnic cleansing campaign.
The UN says almost 150,000 Rohingyas
have fled the country
since the military operation began.
The entire area has been burned out.
The residents are evidently all gone.
(crackling fire)
These satellite images from Human Rights
Watch show the extent of the destruction.
It shows that the government of Burma
does not have the situation under control.
Nobel Peace Prize laureate,
Aung San Suu Kyi, is facing
mounting criticism
for her handling of the violence.
The situation remains
a textbook example of ethnic cleansing.
We're in Burma, where
a historic tragedy has just unfolded.
An ethnic cleansing
committed by a military regime
and ignored by the world's
most praised democracy icon.
Let me take you back
to where it all began.
For 50 years, Burma was held
in a tight grip by a military dictatorship.
The world and the people put
all their hopes in one woman.
Aung San Suu Kyi. She was kept
in house arrest for nearly 20 years
but never gave up
her quest for democracy.
The military was heavily sanctioned
and isolated from the world.
They wanted to befriend the West
but knew that the West
only accepted one currency.
Democracy.
So they announced a road map
that would lead to democratic elections
and to prove their intent
they released their enemy number one.
(people talking in the background)
(sirens)
(bell ringing)
The most prominent of the military
generals took off their green uniforms
and put on
the white, civilian outfits.
Many generals stayed in uniform,
but the country was now to be governed
by the leaders in white.
I never expected to become president
or ever dreamed of becoming one.
After I became president, as head of
the government, I selected the cabinet.
Most of the ministers I chose were
from the previous military government.
Most are well educated
and experienced in what they do.
But neither they nor I had any idea
of how to transition into democracy.
We had been living without democracy
for more than 50 years.
Institutions in those days were
aligned to the military regime.
We had no idea about how to rebuild
the institutions. It was very difficult.
We were thinking,
"This will be so difficult
with the military regime
and democratic government."
It's so different,
a 180 degree turn.
From the top to the bottom,
you obeyed orders.
That is a different style.
(sounds of clapping)
When President Thein Sein
came to power,
I was asked to take responsibility
for the political reform.
And from that time onwards,
I became deeply involved.
Democracy is ruled by the people,
it's for the people.
And the government has to act
in accordance with
the desire of the people.
Whether it is right or wrong.
(sound of gate opening)
(sound of printing machine)
Before 2010, the country was ruled
by military dictators.
The result, as they know themselves,
was widespread poverty.
A failed state, restrictions and
sanctions imposed by Western countries.
And a lot of other issues.
But their intention wasn't to pursue
democratic principles.
Rather, the constitution helps them
prolong the military rule with reforms.
Reforms that help strengthen
good relations with Western countries.
(people talking in the background)
If we think back to the situation, even
in the early 90's, this was a country
which had sanctioned itself. A military
regime that had isolated itself
and was in some ways quite happy
in isolation for a quarter of a century.
If they really wanted to reform
the bureaucracy, to change the mentality,
they needed help and exposure to the
West and the international community.
And help from
the international financial institutions,
like the World Bank,
the IMF and ADB.
And so, because the government
had a very different agenda
than the military regime before, lifting
sanctions suddenly became a priority.
(sound of chair being dragged)
Top generals in the military
were fully aware
that no military rule in any country is
accepted by the international community.
So the military knew that it would have
to hand power to a civilian government.
(sound of chair being dragged)
From the Western countries'
point of view,
military coups and a military playing
a vital role in politics are unacceptable.
In the last 20 years,
we've lived under very strict sanctions.
Politically,
diplomatically, economically.
(sounds of photos being taken)
The president understands,
that without the participation of
Aung San Suu Kyi in the political process
we cannot integrate
with the international community.
Between Aung San Suu Kyi
and the military government,
there is quite a difference of ideas.
So some made a remark
behind the president's back,
saying that he's trying to give
life back to the already dead tiger.
As a few empty seats in Parliament
have to be filled
the leaders in white let Aung San Suu
Kyi participate in bi-elections.
The elections were symbolic
and the stakes were small.
With only 8% of seats contested,
it brought with it little power.
But this was a way of getting inside.
Pro-democracy leader Aung San Suu Kyi has
taken her place in Myanmar's Parliament,
ushering in a new political era
after years of military dictatorship.
The Nobel Peace laureate and
other newly elected members of her party
pledged to safeguard the constitution.
It's quite a change for a woman
who has been incarcerated
most of the last 20 years.
(sounds of photos being taken)
So when we arrived at the Parliament,
there was a lot of media.
I told them: "Hey, rebels are coming,
rebels are coming."
Well, actually we are rebels, because we
have struggled for nearly three decades.
(speaking in Burmese)
And they regarded us as above
ground insurgents. Not underground.
Aung San Suu Kyi and her party
only hold 8% of seats in Parliament,
so at first glance,
they don't seem to have much leverage.
(speaking in Burmese)
I swear to respect the constitution.
Our objective was
to continue our struggle
based on our political principles.
And to get a truly democratic state.
I have tremendous good will
towards the military.
It doesn't bother me to sit with them.
I'm pleased to sit together with them.
But you would like either to reduce
their presence or not have them here?
We would like our Parliament to be
in line with genuine democratic values.
It's not because we want
to remove anybody as such.
Lack of confidence... If you have
to pinpoint the greatest weakness
that's it, lack of trust and confidence.
Nobody trusts anybody.
This is a result of years and years
of dictatorship.
You always have to be careful, you don't
know who is informing on whom.
This lack of trust has seeped into
our very bones, in a sense.
So this does not help
to bring about reconciliation.
While the leaders in white
continued their efforts,
the devil was in the detail.
The military had written a constitution,
in which they had set out
their rules for democracy.
It had become their most sacred book.
It stated that none of the generals could
ever be prosecuted for sins of the past.
(yelling of orders)
Nor could any civilian government
ever rule over the military.
And they would keep security,
border and defence within their power.
(yelling of orders)
A quarter of the seats in Parliament
were reserved for the military
to ensure that the book itself could
never be changed without their will.
It is our main responsibility
to protect the constitution.
According to
the Constitution of Myanmar,
the military's primary duty
is to protect and uphold
the Constitutional Law of Myanmar.
Oh, and one last detail
put in the book:
Aung San Suu Kyi could never become
the country's president.
The military sees
Aung San Sui Kyi as their enemy.
They don't trust her at all.
So to prevent her
from ever becoming president,
they put the clause 59(f)
into the constitution,
specifically to prevent Aung San Suu Kyi
from becoming president.
I think one has to accept that there
are some elements at the military,
who think that they are the only ones
capable of keeping the country together.
This is not surprising, because
they were in power for more than 50...
They still are, in a sense, in power,
because of the constitution.
The first military coup that established
the long-term military rule in Burma
took place in 1962. So if you
count it from then, it's over 50 years.
After 50 years at the helm, it's not
surprising, they got used to thinking
they were the only ones capable
of keeping the country together.
(sounds of photos being taken)
(people talking in the background)
Now there is a new generation
that is yelling and demanding:
"You are our mother."
"We have no hope for our future."
"So please be our saviour."
She has the ability
to become an esteemed leader.
She has clearly declared: "I want to
be president. I will be the president."
She was very clear about that.
But, when you talk about clause 59(f),
the most important part is the (f).
It simply bars Aung San Suu Kyi
of ever becoming president.
As the book couldn't be touched
by anyone but the military,
Aung San Suu Kyi saw only one way
of becoming the country's president:
To talk directly to them and
convince them to remove the clause.
But nobody seemed interested
in such talks.
Only one man
was willing to listen to her.
(talking in Burmese)
(hammering)
Once the third-highest ranking general
in the entire military dictatorship,
Shwe Mann had expected to become
the president in the new democratic era.
But when appointments were made
by the outgoing dictator in 2010,
he was bypassed when
the grand posts were handed out.
Shwe Mann was only given the position
as Speaker of Parliament,
and not even included
in the president's cabinet.
(speaking in Burmese)
The attempt to side-line
an ambitious man should turn out
to cause unexpected troubles
for the leaders in white.
The enemy of your enemy
is your friend.
I think that's what happened.
He is a very smooth operator.
He is a politician.
His colluding with her and the NLD
did severe damage to our party.
(sounds of photos being taken)
He is thinking of
his personal agenda.
He is thinking of those days when
he thought he would become president.
(sounds of photos being taken
and talking in Burmese)
But up until now, Aung San Suu Kyi
has had very little knowledge
of how the government system works.
And what happened in the last 20 years
on the military and government side.
So I think,
whether she liked it or not,
she needed someone who could share
their knowledge and give advice.
She's planning how to play
with these strong people
in the military.
(sounds of photos being taken
and talking in Burmese)
I think that she thinks that
it will be workable with Shwe Mann.
But in politics, there are no friends
and no enemies.
Sometimes you are friends,
sometimes you are enemies.
Sometimes hostility,
and sometimes friendship.
Aung San Suu Kyi thinks
that Shwe Mann will be able to amend
the constitution and the 59(f).
Because to amend it you need
at least one vote from the military.
So she thinks that Shwe Mann
can deliver the result.
Shwe Mann agreed
to discuss a motion in the Parliament
for the amendment of the constitution.
We have already set up a committee
to amend the constitution.
They are now observing
and analysing the constitution.
To amend 59(f) in the constitution...
You'll need the vote
of 75% plus one.
And the army holds
25% of the seats in the Parliament.
It is impossible!
75% plus the military's 25%.
We know that it is impossible.
He pretends to do that.
I support you, I support you...
(sounds of photos being taken)
The rumour was that Aung San Suu Kyi
would eventually make him president.
He knew that amending
the constitution was impossible,
but it would buy her loyalty.
In the event of
a future election victory,
Aung San Suu Kyi
would nominate the president.
Even if she couldn't become one herself.
The Union Parliament continued
its session in Naypyidaw on Thursday.
Members of the Parliament continued
to discuss a section of the bill,
amending the constitution of
the Republic of the Union of Myanmar.
He spent 40 years in the military
together with us.
(people talking in the background)
He betrayed the military. So no one
in the military would accept that.
The amendment bill was not enacted.
Parliament Speaker Shwe Mann
told the legislator,
after the 388 votes
in favour of change
fell below the threshold of
75% of lawmakers needed for it to pass.
(sound of a motorbike)
But things didn't turn out his way.
Having betrayed the military, he never
got the chance to run for the presidency.
When we arrived at the party office
around midnight last night
we saw many police cars circling
the neighbourhood.
There was tight security at
the military party's headquarters.
Activities continued all night, and many
were entering and exiting at midnight.
The head of Myanmar's powerful
ruling party has been ousted.
Shwe Mann,
who is also the Speaker of Parliament,
is said to be effectively
under some form of house arrest.
Conservative forces
strongly linked to the military
appear to have made their move,
by replacing him.
I wasn't the one in charge of that.
Some of the leaders from the party
did that
and made some changes
in the party.
Beforehand, some of the leaders
from the party sent me a letter,
saying that they needed
to do something like that.
I think it was done on 12 August.
Overnight, they had stripped him
of his party duties.
(sound of a motorbike)
You know who did that? Although I don't
know who ordered that transfer of power
my assumption is that
the Old Man...
Senior General Than Shwe,
is still influential.
Nobody else would think about
this leadership change.
Only he can give that kind of order.
(sounds of traffic)
(sound of a car)
Behind the scenes, the Old Man
was still pulling the strings.
He had ruled the country with
an iron fist for two decades.
(sounds of photos being taken)
It was him that had put the sacred book
in place and ordered democracy
and was now watching that
every move was conducted
in accordance with the script.
The day he stepped down,
he divided his power in two,
appointing a civilian president
and a commander of the army.
(yelling of orders)
Aung Hlaing was chosen to lead the army,
because the Old Man checked
his astrology.
That's why he became
commander of the army.
Not his military professionalism.
His stars were at the top.
As the spiritual guardians
of the country,
the monks and the astrologers had
always had a powerful role in society
and a vital say
in all aspects of Burmese life.
The Old Man's biggest fear was the
woman that had always been in his way.
Even with her in house arrest
had he engaged four astrologers
to foresee any threat
that could come from her side.
While the country was holding
its breath
anxiously awaiting
the promised elections
it all depended on one man's will.
With the traitor ousted,
and 59(f) securely in place,
he finally allowed
free and fair elections to go ahead.
They chose the election date:
November 8th, 2015.
One of the top astrologers advised them:
"If it takes place on 8 November 2015,
you will win a landslide victory."
(traffic noise
and people talking in the background)
(people talking in the background)
(speaking in Burmese)
(sounds of demonstration)
(people cheering
and sounds of clapping)
At that time, the surveys
of the whole country said
that they would win, handsomely.
We are 100% confident of winning.
But of course,
we will only know after polling.
But as you know,
the result was quite the opposite.
By dusk, results were coming in
thick and fast.
In one big city,
they captured 100% of votes.
(sounds of cheering)
The Party of the Fighting Peacock.
Aung San Suu Kyi and the people
of Myanmar have waited 25 years
and the NLD, The National League
for Democracy, her party,
has won a crucial majority
to get to this point today.
One of their top astrologers
advised them,
but sometimes they are totally wrong.
After losing the election,
he went to a village and shaved
his head and became a monk.
(sounds of cheering)
(sounds of photos being taken)
The leaders in white stepped down and
let Aung San Suu Kyi take their place.
From now on, she'd have to co-operate
directly with the commander of the army.
The military in its true colours.
With the election victory
new colours filled the Parliament.
Aung San Suu Kyi could lead her party
that now held a ruling majority,
but could never become president.
They would be sitting
next to the military
who stayed to guard the book and
kept key ministries within their power.
It seemed that despite
decades of struggle
she would be tied to them
in ruling the kingdom.
But then, they had always
been bound together.
In the 1940s, General Aung San led
the fight for Burma's independence
against the British colonial powers.
The country needed unity and strength
to gather on the inside and
to protect itself on the outside.
But it was no easy task.
Because the country was rich and varied.
It had rivers and
mountainous areas, hills and jungles.
And a number of ethnic
and religious people:
Karen, Karenni, Chin, Kachin,
Shan, Mon, Rakhine.
Aung San proposed to unite
all the country's people,
and founded
Burma's Independence Army.
By standing together, they could get
the British out. And he succeeded.
It was at an early hour, specially
chosen by Burmese astrologers,
that Rangoon marked Burma's
full assumption of independence.
In place of the Union Jack,
the Burmese national flag was hoisted.
Shortly after, Aung San was brutally
assassinated by political rivals.
Wars broke out with the ethnic people.
The people lost their founding father,
but he had left them a military
and a daughter.
She always mentioned
that she was brought up
in the hands of
the officers around her father.
She had an affection
for whomever was in the army.
But they still do not accept
the role of Aung San Suu Kyi.
It's a personal grudge.
Since the independence,
when her father was assassinated
it was a known fact that
he's the architect of our independence.
He is the founder of the Burma Army.
So they were the sons or grandsons
of General Aung San.
And then when
the military government took over,
army is the father,
army is the mother.
(sounds of traffic)
For now they would share the kingdom and
were tied together as brother and sister.
But she wasn't going to give up her plan
to unseat the military from the palace.
After all, she was the true heir
to the throne.
The constitution bars her
from becoming the president,
but today she threw down the gauntlet
to the Myanmar military.
(speaking in Burmese)
The constitution says nothing about
somebody being above the president.
I am going to be above the president.
- How?
- I have already made plans.
Thank you very much.
(sounds of clapping)
Quite what she intends isn't clear,
but the constitution, she said, would
not present an impossible obstacle.
Despite the military's resistance,
the State Counsellor Law
was passed by a majority vote today.
The military stood in protest,
but the law was passed.
Being State Counsellor means that
the president and all the departments
will be under her control.
It's a very wise step, you see.
And they accused us of,
what was it...
Democratic dictatorship.
Bravo!
I like that terminology.
Being State Counsellor means
that she controls every ministry.
She's like a tiger or a bull. If she
has an idea, she will never let it go.
(laughing)
It started with the lawyer, Ko Ni.
Because he is an expert
in constitutional literature.
So he leafed through all the articles
and he found one loophole.
That the president can create a position
for anybody and give any status.
The most important and the first thing we
need to do is to change the constitution.
I'll make all the decisions.
If I'm required to field a president
who meets the requirements
of section 59(f), we'll find one.
This president will carry out
whatever wish Aung San Suu Kyi has.
And even the president...
He is her school mate.
A very simple,
a soft man, soft-spoken...
The president will carry out everything
that comply with her desire.
So she can do everything now,
more than the president.
Now she can handle everything.
So that is why
we made a clever move,
so that Aung San Suu Kyi
is able to carry out all of the powers.
And we have a majority of the vote
in the Parliament. So we won.
Actually,
she didn't have all the power.
While she had learned the game well
and played by the rules,
the military hadn't left the stage.
And they responded with their language:
(gunshot)
Violence.
(screaming and sirens)
On Sunday afternoon,
Myanmar state-run news, MRTV, reported
that one of the government
legal advisors to Aung San Suu Kyi
was shot and killed by a sole gunman.
Police have a suspect in custody.
Ko Ni was shot dead
at Yangon International Airport
while holding his young grandchild.
Despite many unanswered questions
regarding the murder of Ko Ni,
many here in Myanmar
see it as a sign
the government of Aung San Suu Kyi has
yet to firmly establish the rule of law.
The murder is also seen
as a warning to those
who want to reduce
the power of the military.
Police say his killers motives
weren't political,
but one of his friends believes he was
murdered because of his legal work.
We sensed that
he was hated by some people.
But I didn't expect it
to be that vicious.
Actually, it's a mafia.
Ko Ni was shot directly in the head in
front of The Yangon International Airport.
He was immediately taken to Yangon
Hospital, where he was pronounced dead.
Aung San Suu Kyi
didn't attend the funeral.
She stayed silent and withdrew
from the public eye.
She's shocked.
She can guess the main reason.
If she says something,
it will get worse.
Was it some kind of warning for her?
That if you go too far...
Maybe.
But there was another problem
with this lawyer.
He was a Muslim.
In the country's Rakhine region
lived a Muslim minority group
which the Buddhist Rakhine people
wanted out.
The reason was to be found
in the past.
Back in 1947, when Aung San
had united the country's ethnic people,
one group was believed to have stayed
on the British side.
The ruling Buddhist majority agreed
that they were traitors
and that they did not belong
in the country:
The Muslim Rohingyas.
The Buddhists called them Bengalis,
considered people
that had come from abroad.
If my words are true, all the people
from Rakhine will be free from Bengali.
(cheering)
Our duty is not only
to enforce law and order,
but also to preserve
the identity of the nation.
On the question of race,
we've let the world know that the
Rohingyas don't belong in our country.
The Muslims of Rakhine state
are Bengalis.
They just came here
from other places and settled.
Rakhine was a timebomb
that was ticking.
You had
this rising Rakhine nationalist feeling.
And the two communities, Muslim and
Buddhist, also began to see each other...
Or rather, increasingly saw each other
as their main enemies as well.
And then you had, not surprisingly,
the emergence in 2016
on the Muslim side,
a new insurgency,
and a very militant insurgency.
The group is poorly equipped.
It has guns, small home-made bombs
and what it describes as a narrow
mission: To protect Rohingya Muslims.
(sound of explosion)
(crackling fire)
(crying and sobbing)
An attack on rural police stations by
Rohingya fighters in the Rakhine region
would turn out to have
unforeseen consequences
and lead to a turning point
in the country's history.
Muslim terrorists are destroying and
setting things on fire in Rakhine state.
Locals are running to
the nearest police stations for help.
Authorities say some 150 insurgents
launched a series of raids
on police posts in the early hours.
The Rohingya insurgents carry out these
attacks to get the world's attention.
So what they want most is to attract
concern from the outside world.
For the military, the situation provided
an opportunity to respond
and to get rid of a problem altogether.
The army has begun its "clearance
operations" to root out Rohingya fighters.
The brutal Burmese military operation
against Rohingya Muslims
is at risk of spiralling into
an ethnic cleansing campaign
as the violence against the long
persecuted minority group continues.
The Burmese response was
to close the area.
And the army began what it called
"clearance operations".
Civilians as well as militants
have been targeted.
The army has its own agenda.
Without consulting us, they have
the right to do whatever they like.
(people talking and gunshots)
They can do what they like. We cannot
interfere or order them what to do.
The UN says almost 150,000 Rohingyas
have fled
the predominately Buddhist country
into neighbouring Bangladesh in the
last 12 days since the operation began.
The current situation
cannot yet be fully assessed,
but the situation remains, or seems,
a textbook example of ethnic cleansing.
The international community expected her
to respond and to condemn the military.
The one thing she couldn't do.
The constitution gave her
no power over military affairs.
The consequences of that
were now being realized.
But as the crisis worsened by the
minute, her immediate response was...
Denial.
I am deeply disappointed and saddened
by the disinformation campaign
being waged around the world
with regard to the situation in Rakhine.
These fabricated news items
are written and published
with the intent to mislead the public.
Aung San Suu Kyi, the country's leader,
said the situation in Rakhine state
was being distorted by what she called
"a huge iceberg of misinformation".
The Rakhine thing blew up in our face.
The government has rejected accusations
that the armed forces are conducting
a campaign of indiscriminate violence
targeting Rohingya Muslims.
The Ministries of Home Affairs,
Defence and Border Areas
are controlled by the army.
So when the Rakhine thing happened,
the international community blamed
Aung San Suu Kyi for protecting the army.
But she didn't want to make any hostile
remarks to the army for the long run.
She was blamed for that.
That's why we call it a military trap.
Nobel Peace Prize laureate, Aung San Suu
Kyi, who is Burma's de facto president,
is facing mounting criticism
for her handling of the violence...
The Nobel Peace Prize laureate,
Aung San Suu Kyi,
has blamed terrorists for what she termed
"a huge iceberg of misinformation".
... amounts to ethnic cleansing.
Nobel Peace Prize winners have criticized
Myanmar's leader, Aung San Suu Kyi,
for not doing enough to protect...
She's seeking to deflect
the Rohingya crisis
that has so far sent
150,000 Rohingyas Muslims...
She should use her voice, and she
hasn't, and that's deeply disappointing.
... silent and,
in many cases, a complicit...
When you get power you go into a cocoon.
You go into an us-against-them attitude.
I think that Senior General
Min Aung Hlaing knows the problem
and that he is enjoying the situation.
(sounds of demonstration)
Today there was a popular march
to Yangon City Hall
to support
the military's fair and just war.
More than a thousand attended
to support Myanmar military
and their fair war.
Many Burmese hate the Bengali,
or the Rohingya, they hate them.
So if you are involved in this case,
it shows you are supporting the Rohingya.
So she may keep silent on this thing.
Maybe she worries that she won't have
their vote in the future.
(whistling)
While the military kept
the conflict rolling,
the outside world demanded
clear answers from the state leader.
From their front row seats
in the audience
the military watched her
enter the scaffold.
After intense pressure, Aung San Suu Kyi
addressed the Rohingya refugee crisis.
This televised address to diplomats
was miss Suu Kyi's chance
to state her case to the world.
It is not the intention
of the Myanmar government
to apportion blame or
to abnegate responsibility.
We condemn all human rights violations
and unlawful violence.
We are committed
to the restoration of peace,
stability and rule of law
throughout the state.
The government has been making every
effort to restore peace and stability,
and to promote harmony between
the Muslim and Rakhine communities.
I am aware of the fact,
that the world's attention is focused
on the situation in Rakhine state.
But we would like you to think
of our country as a whole.
Not just as little afflicted areas.
The international community wanted her
to say: "I support the Rohingya people."
But I don't think
she can say things like that.
Because in the long run,
she will have to work with the military.
Aung San Suu Kyi has made her choice.
Her relationship with the military
and the stability of her government
comes before the Rohingya and what
is left of her international reputation.
She went behind closed doors, far away
from the people and the world.
All the while, the country
was falling apart at the seams.
The entire area has been burned out.
The residents are evidently all gone.
It shows a clear swath of destruction,
presumably caused by arson.
These satellite images from Human Rights
Watch show the extent of the destruction.
Once again, the government of Burma does
not have the situation under control.
The 8,333rd meeting of
the Security Council is called to order.
The provisional agenda for this meeting
is the situation in Myanmar.
The massive refugee emergency that
began one year ago in Rakhine state
has become one of the world's worst
humanitarian and human rights crises.
The world can no longer avoid the
difficult truth of what happened in Burma.
The Rohingya population of Rakhine state
was subjected to a campaign of...
... the worst catastrophes
in modern history...
... resulting in grave violations
of their human rights...
... have led to the displacement
of some 900,000 people...
The military and police went
from house to house looking for girls...
... violations and abuses against
the Rohingya community in Rakhine state...
I now give up the floor to
the representative of Myanmar.
Mr President. Our gathering here today
could have been a different one
had there been no terrorist attacks.
It would have been
a happier occasion to stock-taking
implementation of
the Rakhine Advisory Commission
or an international
pledging conference
to help with poverty alleviation...
(... and socio...)
Sorry.
... and socio-economic development
of all communities of Rakhine.
The provocative terrorist attacks
of October 2016 and August 2017
have affected the cause
of our earnest endeavour
to build a peaceful, fair and prosperous
future for the people of Rakhine.
But nothing shall stop
our determination to continue our effort
to achieve our objectives.
So this is what it came to.
Despite so much hope,
they couldn't make it.
History is never over,
but for the story I have told you,
this is, unfortunately, the end.